בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is
קמ"ז. Kaf Mem Zayin. We start at the very bottom of קמ"ו
עמוד ב'. Kaf Mem Vav Amud Bet. We're moving on from food
issues and opening packages to other just very practical applications on שבת.
Shabbat. It's quite interesting that finally now that we get to the
very end of a very long מסכת, masechet, we're finally getting a
whole list of really practical applications. So, the last point in the
משנה mishna spoke about if somebody was walking and got his clothes
soaking wet, some discussion whether it's rain or walking through water, then
when he gets back he can wear them, doesn't have to worry
about incidental סחיטה. skhita. He's not intending for it, whatever, he's not
really doing it, it's just dripping off. But when he gets into
the courtyard and he wants to strip them because, you know, who
wants to be wearing wet clothes? He can lay them in the
sun, but it cannot be in a visible location because people will
think he did laundry on שבת. Shabbat. Let's take a look at
the גמרא, Gemara, three lines from the bottom. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, כל מקום שאסרו חכמים מפני מראית
העין, kol makom she-asru Chachamim mipnei marit ha'ayin, anytime the חכמים Chachamim
made something forbidden because of how it would appear to the eye,
you know, because of appearances,
אפילו בחדרי חדרים אסור. afilu be-chadrei chadarim asur. So things that are
forbidden because of appearances are forbidden even in one's innermost chambers. It
doesn't matter if it's public or private. Now we'll discuss why in
a minute, but let's first see what the גמרא Gemara says about
this. תנן, Tnan, so is that really true? Our משנה mishna says
שוטחין בחמה אבל לא כנגד העם. shotchin bachama aval lo kineged ha-am.
You spread out your clothes that got wet in the sun to
dry out, but you cannot do it in front of the people.
So the
גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, Tannai hi, that's a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, שוטחן בחמה אבל
לא כנגד העם, shotchan bachama aval lo kineged ha-am, you spread it
out in the sun but not in front of
people. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אוסרין, Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Shimon oserin, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say it's forbidden.
So it's a debate of תנאים Tannaim whether we say that something
that is forbidden because of appearances is forbidden only in public or
even in private. By the way, although we, you know, guys that
go to ישיבה yeshiva like have this like a mantra, אפילו בחדרי
חדרים אסור, afilu be-chadrei chadarim asur, you know, and assume that that's
definitely the הלכה, halacha, there are actually some opinions that we rule
that it's not forbidden in private. Well, yeah, I mean we don't,
early positions I'm saying, I think the הלכות גדולות, Hilchos Gedolos, the
בה"ג, Behag, you know, from the גאונים Geonim פוסק paskens that it's
not forbidden in private, it's only forbidden in public. We rule even
in private, that's the overwhelming position. But there is an interesting debate
about what if it's a concern of appearances that it doesn't look
like you did something biblically problematic, like in this case people will
think you're doing laundry on שבת, Shabbat, but it actually will look
like maybe you're doing something rabbinically prohibited? There actually are some פוסקים,
poskim, contemporary פוסקים, poskim, that say that that concern, that even if
they think you're doing something wrong, the worst they'll think you're doing
is something rabbinically wrong, that's not forbidden in private, that's only forbidden
in public. So it's interesting, there are some opinions that some cases
maybe that would be different. Of course, the biggest thing for מראית
העין marit ha'ayin is context,
which means it doesn't matter if, the question is not is anybody
seeing it, but the question is were somebody to be seeing it,
what would it appear like? So for example, if your raincoats get
soaking wet and you hang them up in your bathroom,
you know, nobody thinks that you did your laundry on שבת. Shabbat.
So that's not a problem, okay? So context makes a huge difference.
But the context is different than, you know, where they say like
if, you know, people know that you have פרווה parve cream out
there, then it doesn't matter because everybody understands that's the context, or
particularly if you have the little box, it used to be you
had to have the box of the פרווה parve cream on the
table. Anyway, there's a big difference. There it's what would it look
like were somebody seeing it given the context, and the other is
does somebody happen to be seeing it? So we tend to not
be lenient just because somebody doesn't happen to be seeing it, but
it is not a מראית העין marit ha'ayin question when context makes
it clear that it's another situation. Sholly had a question.
Oh, I was,
you addressed it.
Okay, yeah.
And also זלזול מצוה zilzul mitzvah and that's why, say what? Things
like זלזול מצוה zilzul mitzvah kind of like that you have מראית
עין marit ayin that's like it's for our own purpose.
So I don't know if I'd call it זלזול מצוה, zilzul mitzvah,
but thank you, normally the question is why is מראית העין marit
ha'ayin אסור בחדרי חדרים, asur be-chadrei chadarim, you know, those that it
is? So one could just be it's such a big concern, you
know, you never know who's looking and you might think you're in
private and somebody is watching you and so on. But I think
that what Ari says is definitely true, that one of the issues
about מראית עין marit ayin I think is not just what other
people will think and will that lead them to think either more
poorly of you or be more lenient against the עבירות, aveyrot, but
it's not just about other people, it's also about your own sense
and your own sensibilities. And therefore, doing certain things that have all
of the appearance of being
forbidden also compromise your own sensibilities about your boundaries about these types
of issues. So I do think that that is one of the
reasons, that's my understanding, not the only, but certainly an important reason
why. forbidden even in private. Okay, so now the—is that what—was that
your question or not? Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
at the bottom of the last line, and אמר רב הונא, Amar
Rav Huna, now that we're talking about your clothes getting wet, we're
going to have this whole עמוד Amud discussing various issues about clothes.
המנער טלית בשבת, Hamenayer talit beShabbat, somebody that shakes out his טלית
talit on שבת, Shabbat, חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. So although we've been
mentioning that there's a lot of ambiguity at various places, whether we're
talking about a rabbinic or a biblical prohibition, here it's very straightforward,
you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. Why? Because this is laundering, כיבוס. kibus.
Now how is it laundering? If you look at רש"י, Rashi, top
of the page, המנער טלית מן העפר, hamenayer talit min ha'afar,
right from dust, you get dust inside of your garment, חייב חטאת,
chayav chatat, whatever, דזהו ליבונה, dezehu libunah, that that is its laundering.
Now תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot says המנער טלית פירש ר"ח hamenayer
talit perush Rach מן הטל. min hatal. Now by the way it's
not true. In our רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel it actually says just
like רש"י, Rashi, it's dust. But he says רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
says it means
dew. דהיינו כיבוס וליבון וחייב חטאת. dehainu kibus velibun vechayav chatat. That's
laundering. וכן משמע vechein mashma etcetera. אבל בניער, aval biniyer, the third
line in תוספות, Tosafot, מן האפר, min ha'efer, if you're just getting
rid of the dust, כדפירש בקונטרס אין זה שייך ליבון. kedefireish bekuntres
ein ze shayach libun. It doesn't seem like it would be ליבון.
libun. What is the debate? The debate is, can you have ליבון
libun laundering without water? Right, exactly. They didn't know about dry cleaning.
Well, they actually did, but anyway. But is that, is can even
if you get something dirt out of something, maybe it's just not
defined as laundering without the use of water. Actually רש"י Rashi himself
said that a while ago. רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger points
to that but here רש"י Rashi is saying otherwise and saying that
actually no, if you actually get the embedded dirt out even just
by like vigorously rubbing it, that actually will be ליבון libun even
without water. תוספות Tosafot disagrees a little. By תוספות Tosafot I must
admit, you know, if you've got water on your garments and you
shake it off, why is, you know, why is that really cleaning
your garment? I mean, if you ask me which is more—now you
could say maybe it's not so much the result that the garment
got cleaned, but it's part of the process of laundering, the acts
that are done in the process of laundering. So one of the
acts that are done in the process of laundering is you submerge
something in water. One of the processes is that you squeeze it
out with water. So it's all of the stages in the process.
And by the way, we had discussed squeezing, and there are opinions,
right, that squeezing is considered out water is considered laundering even without
asking the question, "Well, did the garment get cleaner or not?" Maybe
it doesn't matter. Maybe these are just stages. We say, for example,
submerging something in water is considered laundering. Maybe it doesn't matter that
the thing actually got clean. Maybe it just means that it's one
of the stages of the process of laundering. Even so, it would
seem to me, if you ask me which is more an act
of the process of laundering, taking soaking wet clothes and spreading them
out in the sun to dry, which is what we had in
the משנה, Mishna, right, or if you have, you know, your clothes
got wet in the rain, shaking them off, I would certainly think
that putting it in the sun is much more the part of
the laundering process, although maybe that doesn't use water itself, it's about
the evaporating water. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says it's about shaking off
the water. The overwhelmingly the position is like רש"י, Rashi, which is
generally a חומרא, chumra, which means you can have laundering without water.
But also it could be a קולא, kula, it could mean that
a simple shaking off of water is not laundering. But laundering then
focusing on not the process of laundering—getting it wet, squeezing it out,
and so on—maybe that's also true under certain circumstances. But it could
also be laundering just if you're rubbing out, getting, actually effectively, you
know, getting out the embedded dirt. And therefore that is something you've
got to be careful about on שבת, Shabbat, you know, you find
that your shirt has, you know, I don't know, it's got like
powder on it or it did get some dirt on it, so
you can wipe it off of the surface, but vigorous rubbing to
get out what's embedded, that really is laundering. Yes.
And in addition to the squeezing, I would think that not shaking
it off, because you get water on the outside of your garment,
if you shake it off before it gets absorbed by the
garment—right, I agree, I really have a hard time understanding תוספות. Tosafot.
I understand his desire to say water has to be part of
the process, but right, I would say squeezing it out once it's
absorbed, but not shaking. So we generally, overwhelmingly the read of the—we
פוסקין poskin like רש"י Rashi about this, that it's not shaking off
water, but on the other hand, it doesn't require water and there
is a laundering concern about really rubbing out, you know, dirt and
embedded dirt and dust from your garments. Now we're going to qualify
it in a minute, but yes, go ahead ארי. Ari.
It seems like he says regular
shaking, המנער טלית. hamenayer talit.
You mean in terms of—in terms of רש"י, Rashi, of even the
רש"י. Rashi. Even רש"י's Rashi read. It sounds like you're just shaking
it out. Yeah, I know. Let's keep on reading though a little
bit more, because we'll see some qualifications. Yeah, so it says, well,
getting stuff out of—out
of—of cloth, not סתם stam cleaning. You're allowed to, you know, you're
allowed to clean your glasses, clean your tabletop, clean your shoes. Okay,
it's about stuff that's embedded in cloth. Okay, ולא אמרו, velo amru,
now we're going to see some qualifications. ולא אמרו אלא בחדתי, velo
amru ella bechadti, that's only by new garments. אבל בעתיקי לית לן
בה, aval be'atiki leit lan bah, old garments it's not a problem.
Why? Because, you know, it's considered that well, you don't really care
so much. Of course... if you didn't care at all, you wouldn't
be shaking it out. And who cares if you don't care? So
I'm allowed to light a fire if I don't care so much
about it? So, but presumably it means that if you're not really,
you know, that changes the definition of the process. That somehow even
though you're effectively getting dirt out or so on, it's not considered
cleaning and laundering if you're maybe, you know, not really significantly transforming
the garment and it looks old and worn after the fact, you
know, it's not really it's it's
again, part of the reason I would say we're lenient here is
also because you're not doing the classic process. You know, if you
were actually put it in water and put in detergent and squeeze
it, it wouldn't matter if it's old. But given that it's just
about the result of getting it looking good without so much the
process of laundering, so then if you don't care so much, it's
not a real big change, it's not a problem. ולא אמרין אלא
באוכמין, Velo amrin ela be-uchmin, and it's only by black garments. אבל
בחיורי וסומקי, Aval be-chivri ve-sumki, white or red garments, לית לן בה,
leit lan bah, it's not an issue again because then the change
it doesn't it's not you know, dust on a black garment is
much more visible than on these other garments. So the effect of
what you're doing and the fact that it's considered to maybe be
soiled to begin with and therefore cleansed, cleaned after the fact is
less is less the case. והוא Vehu one minute, garments? Well right,
so they maybe that's only if it's dust, right? Maybe it's maybe
I'm sorry, right I'm assuming dust is like this sort of white
dust, whatever. You're right, if it's if it's like dirt dirt, black
dirt, so then the white would be an would be an issue
as well, you know, would be even a bigger issue.
You're ignoring all the סחיטה sechita issues now, right?
Yeah, yeah, this this there's no water here, other than according to
תוספות. Tosafot. והוא דקפיד עליה, Vehu dekpid alei, and all of this
is only if you really care about it. Now of course again,
you care enough to be getting it off, but the question's like
how much caring? So it is interesting all these qualifications, you know,
here you are, you actually are shaking it out, but if you
say, oh we don't care I don't care so much, I you
know so then it's not such an issue. Again, part of this
is because I think that you are not doing the normal process
of laundering. You're not getting it wet, you're not wringing it out,
you're not using detergent. So to be calling this laundering just by
using your hand to get it out, you know, it's only in
very narrow cases where we say you're doing a dramatic change and
it was like deep it was really considered a problem and you're
doing a drastic a drastic change.
So the question is like how much today would you apply these
same things? You'd say it has to be black, you know, would
you just say, under the circumstances where you really care about it.
So if it's white, but it's a certain type of a dirt,
etc. The other interesting issue is how much do you have to
really clean it, completely? Meaning let's say you get a little bit
out, but you don't totally clean it, right? So that none of
that is really sort of fully clarified. But we're going to see
some anyway applications without still fully clarifying the parameters. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: עולא איקלע לפומבדיתא, Ulla ikla le-Pumbedita, Ulla dropped
into Pumbedita, חזא רבנן דקא מנפצי גלימייהו, chaza rabanan deka nafsi gleimaihu,
saw on שבת Shabbos that the rabbis were like, you know, shaking
out their garments. אמר, Amar, he said, כמה מחלן רבנן שבתא, kama
machalin rabanan shabata, the rabbis are desecrating שבת. Shabbos. אמר להו רב
יהודה, Amar lehu Rav Yehuda, so Rav Yehuda said to the rabbis,
to meaning the rabbinic students, נפוצו ליה באפיה, nafsu lei be-apei, go
shake out your garments right in his nose, right in his face,
okay? Meaning and
then show him that we don't agree with him. Right, אנן לא
קפידנן מידי, anan lo kapdinan midi, we don't really care about it
so much, we're not so מקפיד machpid that it be totally clean.
You know, we don't like the again there's some middle level between
we'd rather not have the dirt on us than that you're really
מקפיד. machpid. So we're not so מקפיד machpid that it really be
fully clean and therefore it's not an issue on
שבת. Shabbos. אביי הוה קאי קמיה דרב יוסף, Abaye hava ka kamei
de-Rav Yosef, now Abaye was standing in front of רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, אמר ליה הב לי קומתאי, amar lei hav li kumtai, give
me my hat. חזא דאיכא טלא עלוויה, Chaza de-ika tala alei, so
רב יוסף Rav Yosef saw that there was, now here this is
תוספות Tosafot says טל tal is dew on it, although I will
say that רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel seems to just interpret this word
as a stain. He
said והוה באותה נציצת הטמן vehava be-ota netzisat hatman I don't know
what הטמן hatman means anyway טינוף. tinuf. So anyway but it sounds
like again we're talking about טל, tal, which is what תוספות's Tosafot
approach was. הוה קא מחסם למיתבא ליה, Hava kama-chasim le-meisa lei, he
was hesitating to give it to him because you know
because he's like maybe you know he didn't want to give it
to him with the טל tal on it and he didn't want
him to take it and to shake it or something on שבת.
Shabbos. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said, נפוץ שדי, nefoz shadi, shake
it, throw it, throw the you know to get the dirt out
or the טל tal out. אנן לא קפידנן מידי, Anan lo kapdinan
midi, we're not we're not מקפיד machpid on stuff
like this to get the טל tal out, you know.
Right, but you know again, so somehow there could be an idea
of like I said of wanting it off, but not so מקפיד
machpid like it would be so bad. Maybe מקפיד machpid means to
the degree that you wouldn't wear it if it wasn't, you know.
There's a question to which it's considered like it's really you know
like you've really significantly transformed the garment. So maybe קפידנן kapdinan means
to the level that you wouldn't wear it unless you actually had
done this. Now again, Ari's point is also a good one because
the the language besides the question of dirt or water sounds more
like just a simple shaking off.
And maybe that's also why all these qualifications, you know, maybe if
it was a vigorous, you know, rubbing out and it was more
deeply embedded it would be a bigger problem. As a general rule
we say that if you can lightly brush stuff off that's on
the surface then that's not cleaning, that's just something's laying. on the
surface and you're brushing it off. That it only begins to be
a problem when you're getting it out from being embedded,
but Ari is right to point out that the language of the
גמרא Gemara sounds like what we're talking about even something that's more
surface level.
Okay, what about like a hard crust though,
you allowed to scrape it off? Possibly. Okay, let's take a look.
Although you mean because there at least it's adhering even though it's
not embedded? Yeah, it's a good question.
I have to get back to
you
on that. אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rav
Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan. So
now
Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef said in the name of
Rabbi Yochanan. היוצא בטלית מקופלת מונחת על כתפו. Hayotzei betallis mekupeles munachas
al kesefo. If you have a טלית tallis that is folded up
and on your shoulder. Now that could just
mean, and I think I might have explained this when we did
this because we've quoted this before or something like this, as actually
literally like you fold it all up like you would put it
away in your drawer and instead you carry it on your shoulder.
Now that's obvious that it's carrying, what's the חידוש? chiddush? But here
it becomes much clearer that what that means is, is that rather
than the normal way you would wear it... by the way, a
טלית tallis here does not mean a ritual garment with fringes. It
means, you know, just a type of a cape that they would
wear. So normally the way you would wear it is that it
would drape low behind your back, like you know we wear our
טליתות. tallisos. Let's say instead of having it drape below, you bundle
it all up from behind and you have it essentially like a
scarf. Okay? So there the point is, even though you're still wearing
it, that's not how you wear a טלית, tallis, and that's defined
not as a wearing, that's defined as carrying. Okay? So if it
was folded and on your shoulder בשבת חייב חטאת, beShabbos chayav chatas,
you're חייב chayav if you wear it out in the street for
carrying. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: סוחרי כסות
היוצאין
בטליתות מקופלות, Socharei kesus hayotzin betallisos mekupallos, if people who sell garments
go out with their טליתות tallisos sort of folded over ומונחות על
כתפיהם umunachos al kispheihem around their
shoulders, בשבת חייבין חטאת, beShabbos chayavin chatas, they're חייב chayav a חטאת.
chatas. ולא סוחרי כסות בלבד אמרו, Velo socharei kesus bilvad amru, now
this is all straight from the ברייתא Baraisa to explain itself, when
they said this they weren't referring, they... it's interesting because I guess
it's commenting on an even earlier teaching... it's not only true about
people that sell garments, אלא כל אדם, ella kol adam, anybody that
wears this טלית tallis this way, אלא שדרכן של סוחרי כסות לצאת
כך, ella shedarkan shel socharei kesus latzes kach, this is the way
sellers go out and therefore we use that as a good illustration.
Even so, maybe to say even though it's the way, right, they're
חייב chayav or maybe the reason they do it this way is
it's a convenient way of carrying their garments and that demonstrates that
this is a type of carrying, not exactly obvious which way that
goes. But anyway, it's still for anybody including them it's considered carrying.
וכן חנווני היוצא במעות הצרורין לו בסדינו, Vichen chanvani hayotzei bema’os hatzrurin
lo bisedino, and if a storekeeper goes out with money bound up
in his like belt, you know, which is how they... you know
so you're wearing like a money pouch, חייב
חטאת, chayav chatas, you're חייב. chayav. ולא חנווני בלבד אמרו, Velo chanvani
bilvad amru, not only him, אלא כל אדם, ella kol adam, anybody,
אלא שדרכן של חנווני לצאת כך, ella shedarkan shel chanvani latzes kach,
normally that's it, so we had a particularly focus on him to
tell him be careful not to do it, but it's true about
anybody, it's not considered wearing, it's considered carrying on your body. והרתנים,
Veharattanim, so even though those things are forbidden, the following is allowed.
רתנים, Rattanim, now רש״י Rashi says it's the name of a people,
the ערוך Aruch says it means like messengers, you know, people that
run. So runners, I guess we even call them, right? Isn't that
what they call them on the stock market floor, like runners or
something? So runners יוצאין בסודרין שעל כתפיהם, yotzin besudarin she’al kispheihem, they
actually can go out with their, you know, with their like
סודר sudar which could be, you know, like a type of a
head covering... the גרא Gra actually says that this actually could be
talking of, just so you... yeah, I'm sorry... so some type of
like, you know, of like a scarf, and there you can actually
wear it sort of, you know, rolled up and around their shoulder.
ולא רתנים בלבד אמרו, Velo rattanim bilvad amru, not only they, אלא
כל אדם, ella kol adam, anybody can do it, אלא שדרכן של
רתנים לצאת כך, ella shedarkan shel rattanim latzes kach, this normally is
the way. So why is this different? Right. So anyway, why is
this different? So this is because this actually is a way that
it is worn. It's not just a way that it is carried,
it is a way that it is worn. Now, you might actually
say one minute, you know, the reason that the runners are doing
it is because when you're running things will fall off, so therefore
you change the way they're on your body so they don't fall
off, which does not necessarily mean that's how you wear it. So
that's why it actually could be a big חידוש, chiddush, that even
though they're running and they might be doing it so it doesn't
fall off, if this is maybe a normal way in which people
wear it, you know, think about like a scarf, right, sometimes you
wear a scarf like unfolded, sometimes you wrap it up and do
it like that. So here it is considered enough the normal way
to wear it, not just a way of carrying, and it's not
a problem. Yes?
Is it מותר muttar to run on שבת? Shabbos?
Well, no, but actually the טור Tur quotes an opinion that you
can if you get enjoyment out of it. but we're not talking
that you're doing this on שבת, Shabbat, we're just talking about these
are this is your profession. So maybe don't think that for you
it's defined differently what it means to wear this thing than for
somebody else. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda מעשה בהורקנוס בנו
של רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס maaseh beHorkenos beno shel Rabbi Eliezer ben
Horkenos שיצא בסודרו על כתפו בשבת, sheyatza besudaro al ketefo beShabbat, he
went out with this like scarf around on his shoulders on שבת,
Shabbat, אלא שנימא כרוכה לו באצבעו, ela shenimah kerucha lo beetzbao,
there was a string attached to his finger which seems like weird,
but somehow that would be a normal way maybe to somehow to
keep it on so that would maybe be more a normal way
to wear it. It's hard to exactly imagine the string on the
finger keeping the stuff on your shoulders. Anyway, וכשבא דבר לפני חכמים
uchesheba davar lifnei chachamim
when it came to the sages אמרו amru they said אפילו אין
נימא כרוכה לו באצבעו. afilu ein nimah kerucha lo beetzbao. You don't
even need that. This is a normal way to wear this folded
up even without it necessarily being like bound onto your body in
any additional way. Okay. דרש רב נחמן בר יצחק משמיה דרב חסדא
Darsh Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mishmei deRav Chisda הלכה אף על פי
שאין נימא כרוכה לו באצבעו. halacha af al pi sheein nimah kerucha
lo beetzbao. That's the way we rule even without some extra string
being wrapped on your fingers to keep it on your body. עולא
איקלע לבי אסי. Ulla ikla lebei Assi. So before עולא Ulla dropping
into פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, here עולא Ulla came to the house of לבי
אסי בר היני. lebei Assi bar Hini. בעו מיניה, Bau minei, so
the people in the house asked from עולא, Ulla, מהו לעשות מרזב
בשבת? mahu laasot marzev beShabbat? Can you make a like a pipe
on שבת? Shabbat? We actually had that before about the wine. Here
it's not exactly clear
what the heck does this have to do and it's in the
context of clothes. So basically it's going to mean according to רש״י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot as they explain different problems that it means
like creating creases. Imagine that you have
like some type of of a טלית tallis going down and you
actually want to like create folds and creases on part of it,
so or folds in your pants, folds in your skirt. Can you
do that? Right. Can you... no, but here the question is is
that like the way רש״י Rashi understands the issue, let me explain
there's a debate. רש״י Rashi understands that the problem is it's like
making a כלי kli maybe at least rabbinically, making permanent folds of
a garment because that's the way you want the garment configured. תוספות
Tosafot understands that no, the question is that this is a way
of folding it up and is this considered to be a way
of wearing it or is this like the issue we discussed before
and that's actually a way of just bundling it up so it
doesn't fall off and therefore it's more like carrying and less like
wearing? So תוספות Tosafot has it as a consistent discussion from what
is before. It's also the way the רמב״ם Rambam has it. It's
also what it seems like from the end of this גמרא Gemara
as we'll get to that it's much less about making creases in
your garment for the concern is making a garment, that it's a
question about carrying. So let's see what the answer is. So they
said can you make this like מרזב? marzev? אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, הכי אמר רבי, hachi amar Rabbi, אסור לעשות
מרזב בשבת. assur laasot marzev beShabbat. רבי Rabbi says it's אסור assur
to make מרזב marzev on שבת. Shabbat. מאי מרזב? Mai marzev? What's
this מרזב? marzev? אמר רב זירא Amar Rav Zera כיסי בבליתא. kisei
bavlayita. So like like little pouches of the Babylonians which okay like
again so they say it means like these like pleated creases in
the garment. But what's the issue? So let's take a look. רב
ירמיה הוה יתיב קמיה דרב זירא. Rav Yirmiyah hava yativ kamei deRav
Zera. רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah was in front of רב זירא. Rav
Zera. אמר ליה, Amar lei, הכי מאי? hachi mai? What if I
do it this way? It doesn't tell us what way but he
says how about this? Is this okay? אמר ליה אסור. Amar lei
assur. והכי מאי? Vehachi mai? What if I do it this way?
אמר ליה אסור. Amar lei assur. That's also אסור. assur. Okay now
you really see why a picture is worth a thousand words because
how are we supposed to know how he did it? So anyway,
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa נקיט האי כללא בידך. nakit hai
klala beyadach. So here רב פפא Rav Papa is going to come
to try to help us here. Take have this take this principle.
כל אדעתא דלכנופי, Kol adaata delechnufei, if you're doing it to bundle
it up, אסור. assur. כל דלהתנאות, Kol deleitnaot, anything that it's to
make it look nice, שרי, shari, it's permissible. So according to רש״י,
Rashi, לכנופי lechnufei means that you're trying to make permanent creases in
the garment as opposed to just make it look nice right now
by the way it's on you. According to רמב״ם Rambam and תוספות,
Tosafot, לכנופי lechnufei means you're trying to like pick it off the
floor so it doesn't get dirty, you're trying to bundle it up
so it doesn't fall off of you as you wear it. So
if you're trying to bundle it up and you're not doing it
as a way of wearing it, then it's carrying. If you're doing
it because it looks nicest this way, then it's wearing and not
carrying it
as something on you.
No, but the question is at what stage even if you're wearing
something do we say what you're doing is you're carrying it on
your body? Like if I were to take my jacket like this,
right, and and have my jacket, we'll use this as an example.
Okay, if I were to have this on me like this, we
wouldn't say I was wearing it, right? Okay, so that's the issue.
At what stage when you start folding it up are you no
longer are you no longer are you no longer carrying but are
you no longer wearing but are you carrying? Some say the issue
is that before the point was was that you went that when
it was definitely carrying was that you took it off the ground
and you folded all the back up and now it's all around
your neck. Here maybe the issue is more that it's like bundled
off to one side. Like as opposed to having it on two
sides of your body, you folded it over and it's all like
on one side of your body. You know how sometimes like the
you know they have those like the Roman senators they go with
the togas and they have this like thing draped over. It sounds
like that's how תוספות Tosafot is discussing it. So does if you
put from one side to the other, is it like you're trying
to wear it that way or is it that you're just trying
to carry it that way?
And then talking about lifting up your hem because you don't want
to get in a puddle kind of?
Well, the רמב״ם Rambam says that that's the issue, but again, the
question is, no, to lift it up like that is not an
issue because then you're still wearing it, you're just holding it up.
Here the point is because you don't want to get in a
puddle, you roll it all up and you change its whole configuration
and now you might not be considered wearing it anymore. Yeah. I
see.
I actually
in places where there's no עירוב eruv guys wearing their טלית tallis
to שול shul on שבת. Shabbos. Yes.
So they're wearing their טלית. tallis. So that's fine. Okay. If they
were doing it like bundled up around their neck or in some
way that it wasn't the normal way to wear it, then it
wouldn't help. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. כי הא דרב
ששת... Ki had deRav Sheshes... כי
הא דרב שישא בריה דרב אידי מיסנא בסידינו הוה. Ki had deRav
Shisha brei deRav Idi misna b'sadino hava. רב שישא Rav Shisha the
son of רב אידי Rav Idi was, you know, was sort of,
you know, sort of dressing himself up, looking nice in his, you
know, in his cloak, in his garment. כי אתא רב דימי אמר,
Ki asa Rav Dimi amar, so when רב דימי Rav Dimi came,
he said, פעם אחת יצא רבי לשדה, Pa'am achas yatza Rebbi lesadeh,
so he said, okay,
okay, so fine. I'm sorry, I put the break in the wrong
place. So, כי הא דרב שישא בריה דרב אידי מיסנא בסידינו הוה.
Ki had deRav Shisha brei deRav Idi misna b'sadino hava. Okay, so
כי אתא רב דימי Ki asa Rav Dimi when רב דימי Rav
Dimi came, אמר פעם אחת יצא רבי לשדה, amar Pa'am achas yatza
Rebbi lesadeh, once רבי Rebbi went out to the field, והיו שני
צדי טליתו מונחים על כתפיו, v'hayu shenei tziddei talliso munachim al ketafav,
the two edges sides of his טלית tallis were on his shoulders.
So again, presumably it means that it's all folded over on one
side of your body, still maybe draped, but all folded over on
one side. אמר לפניו יהושע בן זירוז, Amar lefanav Yehoshua ben Ziruz,
so יהושע בן זירוז Yehoshua ben Ziruz said to רבי, Rebbi, בן
חמיו של רבי מאיר, ben chamiv shel Rebbi Meir, and he was
רבי מאיר'ס, Rebbi Meir's, sounds like brother-in-law, the son of רבי מאיר'ס
Rebbi Meir's father-in-law,
בזו לא חייב רבי מאיר חטאת? B'zu lo chiyyeiv Rebbi Meir chattas?
In this, would רבי, Rebbi would רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir not be
מחייב mechayyev somebody a חטאת? chattas? Meaning he didn't want to say
to רבי Rebbi you're being מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, so he said
it in a more rhetorical way. But he says, really? You know,
would רבי, Rebbi, would רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. not be מחייב mechayyev
somebody a חטאת chattas in this situation? סו אמר ליה, So amar
lei, so רבי Rebbi said to him, דקדק רבי מאיר עד כאן?
Dikdik Rebbi Meir ad kan? What? רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was so
like precise that even this type of a thing, you know, which
is, you know, which he would consider to be not wearing but
carrying? שילשל רבי טליתו, Shilshel Rebbi talliso, so he, so he lowered
back his, you know, he redraped his garment the normal way. So
he sort of, you know, he at least, maybe he was a
little bit astounded but he at least conformed to the position of
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. כי אתא רבין אמר, Ki asa Ravin amar,
לא יהושע בן זירוז הוה אלא יהושע בן קופסאי הוה. Lo Yehoshua
ben Ziruz hava ela Yehoshua ben Kupsai hava. When רבין Ravin came,
he said, it wasn't יהושע בן זירוז, Yehoshua ben Ziruz, it was
יהושע בן קופסאי, Yehoshua ben Kupsai, אבי חתנו של רבי עקיבא, aviv
chasno shel Rebbi Akiva, and it actually wasn't the son of the
father-in-law, it was the actual father-in-law of not רבי Rebbi מאיר but
of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Okay. אמר בזו לא חייב רבי עקיבא
חטאת? Amar B'zu lo chiyyeiv Rebbi Akiva chattas? And he said to
רבי, Rebbi wouldn't רבי, Rebbi, would רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva not be
מחייב mechayyev somebody a חטאת chattas if they wore their garment that
way? אמר לו דקדק רבי עקיבא עד כאן? Amar lo Dikdik Rebbi
Akiva ad kan? What? רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva was so precise even
in such a case to say that, you know, carrying, doing it
on one side of the body would not be acceptable? שילשל רבי
טליתו. Shilshel Rebbi talliso. So he, he redraped, same result. כי אתא
רב שמואל בר רב יהודה אמר נישול איתמר. Ki asa Rav Shmuel
bar Rav Yehuda amar Nishol itmar. It wasn't said that רבי Rebbi
actually was wearing it that way, it said that רבי Rebbi, raised
a question whether you're allowed to, right? Because otherwise this, you know,
could be a disturbing story, it sounds like רבי Rebbi was מחלל
שבת mechallel Shabbos according to רבי עקיבא or רבי מאיר. So there's
another version that he didn't actually do it. Okay, now we, so
that is again an interesting discussion about how you could be wearing
something, but if at a certain point it's no longer considered like
you're wearing it, it's considered like you're carrying it on your body.
Now we go
on. Since we've been talking about getting things wet, which gets us
back to the squeezing issue and we have some issues about laundering,
we have another issue here about squeezing. סו הרוחץ במי מערה ובמי
טבריא, So Ha'rochetz b'mei me'ara u'v'mei Tveriah, if somebody bathes in a
cave water or in the hot springs of Tiberias, ונסתפג, v'nistapeig, which
you and dries himself off on שבת. Shabbos. Now, are you allowed
to bathe in hot water on שבת? Shabbos? We'll talk about that
in a minute, but the focus here is going to be on
drying yourself off. סו אפילו בעשרה אלונטיות, So afilu b'eser aluntiyos, even
if you use ten towels, לא יביאם בידו, lo yevi'em b'yado, you
cannot bring them, you cannot bring them home even if it's all,
you know, a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and it's all a חצר,
chatzer, because if you start, you're allowed to dry yourself, but if
you start carrying them you'll come to squeeze them. So this is
in direct contrast to the previous משנה. Mishnah. Your clothes get wet,
you can wear them. Okay, we're not concerned you'll come to squeeze
them. But carrying a towel, maybe there wasn't anything you could have
done about it anyway, but carrying a towel, we're not going to
ask you to strip in the middle of the street, but carrying
a towel, there we are concerned you'll come to squeeze it if
we let you carry it, even if they are ten towels so
each one is not too wet. אבל עשרה בני אדם, Aval asara
benei adam, but ten people, מסתפקים באלונטית אחת, mistapkim b'aluntis achas, they
can even use one towel, which it'll totally get very wet, פניהם
ידיהם ורגליהם, peneihem yadeihem v'ragleihem, their face and hand and feet, רש״י
Rashi says it could even be their whole body, the point all
is, you know, that's just the normal way, but it means they
could get very wet, ומביאין אותן בידם, u'mevi'in osan b'yadan, and they
can bring it in their hands. Why? Because since they're many people,
they will remind one another not to squeeze it. So therefore there's
not a concern that they will come to squeeze it when it's
many people. So this is a general principle that if a lot,
often if a lot of people are involved, we're less concerned you'll
inadvertently do something. So I just have to say, say, say. So
I just have to say that when I think it was probably
five to seven years ago when my son was maybe somewhere six
seven years old, anyway, we were learning משניות שבת. Mishnayos Shabbos. So,
you know, after many many weeks, we had gotten to the end.
Twenty-three. And we were reading this and he said to me, he
said, "Oh, just like that other thing we taught." I said, "What
are you talking about?" So he took the book, it was like
this picture book, it's great, I don't know if you've seen it,
this משניות שבת Mishnayos Shabbos with pictures. It's fabulous because then you
could just like, you know, you remember so much better with pictures.
Flipped all the way to the beginning, to the end of the
first פרק, Perek, where it talks about lowering the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach into the oven right before שבת Shabbos and it's not a
concern you'll come to stir the ashes because there's multiple people and
it's a group of people doing it. So anyway, so I was
very I got a lot of נחת nachas from that. So anyway,
okay.
So this means you go to a hot spring you can't bring
your towel back?
Well, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara is going to conclude. The
גמרא Gemara is going to פסקן pasken more leniently. Okay. Okay. ומביאים
אותן בידם umevi'im osan beyadam
so they can bring it in their hands if there's a group
of people. סכין וממשמשים sachin u'memashmeshin you can put oil on your
body and you can like and you can like, you know, sort
of smooth, you know, move, you know, smooth it on your body,
you know, rub it in your body, אבל לא מתעמלין aval lo
misamlin you cannot like really like vigorously massage it in because these
these types of things are going to be seen as essentially a
type of, you know, either רפואה, refuah, health, or עובדא דחול uvda
dechol much more weekday type of activity.
You can't get a massage even without the oil then, right?
If it's a type of, yeah, that that is correct. I mean
again, I'm not פסקןing pasken here, you know, because sometimes people really
have need to get a certain massage for pain on שבת Shabbos
and whatever and also gets general issues when somebody is a חולה,
choleh, you know, you know, the prohibitions of רפואה refuah don't apply.
Okay. ולא
מתגררין velo misgarerin and you also cannot like scrape your skin. Apparently
after they would rub oil, after they'd rub oil they'd have these
scrapers. Again, Steinzaltz has this great picture of an ancient sort of
scrapers, they looked to me like a like like, you know, a
measuring spoon, but anyway like it's all on a ring and it's
different sizes. But they would use it apparently to get the oil
off and it makes sense that they are little spoons because, you
know, you're spooning off the oil but you're also like rubbing the
body. So that you can't do. אין יורדין
לקורדימא ein yordin leKordima you can't go to קורדימא Kordima which is
basically like a type of a river with that has a muddy
bottom, we'll see why. ואין עושין אפיקטויזין ve'ein osin apiktvizin
and you cannot make actually a what's this called? A purgative, something
that makes you throw up. Okay. They had that. This was quoted.
ואין מעצבין את הקטן ve'ein me'atzvin es hakatan you can also not
do certain things to align the limbs of of a minor. ואין
מחזירין את השבר ve'ein machzirin es hashever and you cannot return and
you cannot sort of reset a broken bone. Now, we mostly no
we don't פסקן pasken by any of this because most like almost
all of these are חולה. choleh. You know, we would consider it
to be חולה, choleh, לא חולה שיש בו סכנה lo choleh sheyesh
bo sakana but at least חולה כל הגוף choleh kol haguf where
these types of concerns do not apply. What's fascinating is that the
גמרא Gemara didn't consider them that. But again, you know, our scope
of applying these prohibitions around רפואה refuah is much narrower.
Since how do we explain the איסור issur in the משנה Mishna
then?
I don't know. מי שנפרקה ידו ורגלו mi shenifreka yado veraglo if
somebody has dislocated a leg or a shoulder, לא יטרפם בצונן lo
yetarfeim betzonen do not sort of, you know, immerse them in cold
water, which I guess they would do to to make it less
painful. אבל רוחץ הוא כדרכו aval rochetz hu kedarko but you can
wash normally. ואם נתרפא נתרפא ve'im nisrape nisrape and if he gets
better, he gets better, but it cannot be an obvious health type
of thing. Again, all these types of things we would immediately say
that all of these are חולה כל הגוף, choleh kol haguf, right?
So it's shocking again that the משנה Mishna puts it in the
category of the איסור רפואה, issur refuah, but you know, we have
we much more define the איסור רפואה issur refuah in much more
narrow circumstances למעשה. lema'aseh. So let's take a look.
Someone ran with?
Yeah, yeah, apparently. Let's take a look what?
It was just signed by an animal.
Animals? Maybe. I don't think so. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. קתני מי מערה דומיא דמי טבריא. katani mei me'ara
dumya de'mei Tverya. So the first point is it says well water,
you know, cave water, similar to hot springs of טבריה. Tverya. מה
מי טבריא חמין, ma mei Tverya chamin, hot springs of טבריה Tverya
are hot water. אף מי מערה חמין, af mei me'ara chamin, even
these are hot. Now, you would see that that would suggest that
that you're allowed to do hot water immersion in שבת. Shabbos. But
we know as a general rule that the Rabbis forbade you to
immerse in hot water on שבת Shabbos that was that was heated
up by fire, as opposed to if it's like מי טבריא, mei
Tverya, you're allowed to. If it was heated by the sun or
heated naturally. But if it was heated by fire, you are allowed
you
are forbidden to immerse in it on שבת Shabbos because it'll lead
to going to bathhouses and actually heating it up on שבת. Shabbos.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הרוחץ דיעבד אין לכתחילה לא. harochetz diavad
in lechatchila lo. That's why it says הרוחץ, harochetz, one who already
did it. בדיעבד, bediavad, you weren't supposed to have immersed yourself. מי
טבריא mei Tverya would be okay, but you weren't supposed to have
immersed yourself in other hot water that was heated up by
fire even if it's even if it was heated before
שבת. Shabbos. מכלל דלהשתטף כל גופו אפילו לכתחילה שפיר דמי mikal d'lehishtatef
kol gufo afilu lechatchila shapir dami
that the only problem would be immersing yourself, but to actually shower,
pour hot water over your body, that actually would be allowed. It's
Rabbi Shimon, it's Rabbi Shimon. דתניא: De-tanya: לא ישתטף אדם בין בחמין
בין בצונן, דברי רבי מאיר. Lo yishtatef adam bein be-chamin bein be-tzonen,
divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir says you cannot take a shower in
hot or cold water. רבי שמעון מתיר, Rabbi Shimon matir, Rabbi Shimon
permits it. רבי יהודה אומר בחמין אסור ובצונן מותר. Rabbi Yehuda omer
be-chamin assur u-ve-tzonen muttar. Hot water is forbidden, that's part of the
prohibition that you'll come to heat up the water, but cold water
is allowed. So technically speaking, we actually rule this way that the
actual prohibition is really only immersing and not taking a
shower. So if there's different positions about using hot water in an
apartment building on שבת Shabbos or using hot water in your home
which is more problematic because in an apartment building whatever I don't
want to go into all the details. But assuming our scenario where
you could use hot water on שבת, Shabbos, right, so would you
be allowed to take a shower? And technically the answer would be
yes. I mean you'd have to be concerned about hair getting wet
and סחיטה sechita and soap, using liquid soap and not solid soap
and so on. But anyway,
as a general rule we obviously don't do that on שבת, Shabbos,
יום טוב Yom Tov is a different story,
but there is but there is that possibility based
on based on this גמרא Gemara that the basic גזירת מרחצאות gezeirat
merchata'ot has to do with immersing and not with and not with
showering.
Is there any reason we're so מחמיר machmir is because we're concerned
you'll come to all the peripheral things? Basically yeah.
Okay, ונסתפג אפילו בעשרה אלונטיאות. u-nistapeg afilu be-asara aluntia'ot.
So now you can dry yourself even with like ten towels. So
right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רישא רבותא קמשמע לן
וסיפא רבותא קמשמע לן. reisha revuta kamashma lan ve-seifa revuta kamashma lan.
The beginning tells us a חידוש chiddush and the end tells us
a חידוש. chiddush. רישא רבותא קמשמע לן, reisha revuta kamashma lan, the
beginning
tells us a חידוש, chiddush, דאפילו הני דלא נפישי בהו מיא, de-afilu
hanei de-lo nefishi behu maya, this is pretty straightforward פשט pshat of
the משנה, Mishna, that even though even if you use ten towels
that there's not a lot of water in each towel, כיון דחד
הוא, keivan de-chad hu, since it's one person, אתי לידי סחיטה ati
lidei sechita you might come to squeeze and we don't let you
carry it home. וסיפא רבותא קמשמע לן, ve-seifa revuta kamashma lan, and
the סיפא seifa tells us a חידוש, chiddush, אפילו הני דנפישי בהו
מיא, afilu hanei de-nefishi behu maya,
even even if it's ten people using one towel so that there's
a lot of water, כיון דרבים נינהו, keivan de-rabbim ninhu, since it's
a lot of people, מדכרי אהדדי midkhrei ahadadi they remind one another
we're not afraid you'll come to squeeze it. Okay.
But would you be actually squeezing it if it's like soaking wet?
Yeah, but then are you really squeezing it or is it just
dripping? תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Okay, our rabbis taught.
But yeah, there is question like the גמרא Gemara before touched about
using a sponge and sometimes just holding it will cause it to
drip. So okay, some maybe if that were the case it wouldn't
be a wouldn't be a problem. When exactly we're concerned about that
incidental type of a thing is also not so clear. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabbanan. Okay, our rabbis taught. מסתפג אדם באלונטית ומניחה בחלון. mistapeg
adam be-aluntit u-menichah be-chalon. You can dry yourself off in a towel
and put it in the window. So again, here you're putting it
in the window to dry off similar to the idea of the
wet clothes, we're not concerned it looks like doing laundry. But again,
maybe people understand that by your towels you didn't do laundry, they
got wet because you used them on שבת. Shabbos. So that's the
putting it in the window to dry off. But it also says:
ולא ימסרנה לאוליירין מפני שחשודים על אותו דבר. ve-lo yimsarenah le-ulyarin mipnei
she-chashudim al oto davar.
Don't give it to the bathhouse attendants because they are suspect for
if you give them the towel, they'll wring it out. So don't
give them the towel, okay? רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, but
and apparently
you went to the bathhouse, right, מסתפג באלונטית אחת ומביאה בידו לתוך
ביתו. mistapeg be-aluntit achat u-mevia be-yado le-toch beito.
You can even use one towel and
you don't only hang it in the window, you can actually bring
your towel back home from the bathhouse. Again, assuming that there's no
carrying concern, it's all a רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. So he's disagreeing
with our
משנה. Mishna. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף. Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef.
So אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף Rav Yosef his rebbe, הלכתא
מאי? hilkhata mai? How do we rule? Is do we rule that
it's אסור assur or מותר? muttar? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, הא רבי שמעון הא רבי
הא שמואל הא רבי יוחנן. ha Rabbi Shimon, ha Rabbi, ha Shmuel,
ha Rabbi Yochanan. There's all these rabbis that say it's מותר, muttar,
so it's מותר. muttar. Which are all the rabbis? רבי שמעון הא
דאמרן, Rabbi Shimon ha de-amran, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we just said
in the ברייתא. braisa. רבי, here's where we see רבי says it's
מותר. muttar. דתניא, De-tanya, taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי. amar
Rebbi. Said רבי, כשהיינו למדים תורה אצל רבי שמעון בתקוע, keshe-hayinu lemedim
Torah etzel Rabbi Shimon be-Takoa,
when we were learning תורה Torah by רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in
תקוע. Takoa. Presumably this is רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, but yeah, it's the same רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Okay, היינו מעלים שמן ואלונטית מחצר לגג ומגג לקרפף עד
שהיינו מגיעין אצל מעיין שהיינו רוחצין בו. hayinu ma'alim shemen ve-aluntit me-chatzer
le-gag u-mi-gag le-karpef ad she-hayinu magi'in etzel ma'ayan she-hayinu rochtzin bo.
We would bring oil and obviously apparently they would put on the
oil after as part of the during the time that they would
be doing their bathing, maybe after, I don't know if after or
before. Anyway, we would bring the oil and the towels from courtyard
to a roof and from a roof to a sort of an
enclosed yard until we would come to the wellspring which we would
actually bathe in on שבת. Shabbos. So first of all they'd bathe
in a wellspring on שבת, Shabbos, at least it was presumably cold
water. It could have been hot if it was like the hot
springs of טבריה. Teveria.
And the and the and they would be using towels and presumably
although it's not so clear, right presumably it means because it says
we would bring, but somehow the גמרא Gemara understands that that means
that each individual could carry his own towel and it's seen as
an individual and not as a group, so it's not so clear
why it's seen that way. תוספות Tosafot says maybe it has to
do with the fact that the students of a rabbi
were... So therefore, it's assumed that רבי would do it himself. But
anyway, the גמרא Gemara does see that as another proof that you
could carry your towel home. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
or continues, where was I? שמואל דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Shmuel
d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, מסתפג אדם באלונטית ומביא בידו
לתוך ביתו. mispagek adam b'aluntis umiviya b'yado l'toch beito. Same straight פסק.
psak. You can dry yourself with towel, bring it home. רבי יוחנן
דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan d'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה כהלכה היא, halacha k'halacha hi, מסתפג אדם
באלונטית ומביא בידו לתוך ביתו. mispagek adam b'aluntis umiviya b'yado l'toch beito.
Also straight פסק. psak. Okay, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי, umi amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi, could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan actually פסקן pasken it's
מותר? muttar? והרי אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, v'harei amar Rabbi
Yochanan halacha k'stam mishnah, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we always rule
like a סתם משנה, stam mishnah, ותנן, u'tnan, our משנה mishnah says
נסתפג אפילו בעשר אלונטיות לא יביאם בידו, nistapeg afilu b'eser aluntiot lo
yavi'em b'yado, even if he used ten towels, he can't bring them
home if it's one person. So how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say that it's allowed to? ההוא כבן הכינאי מתני ליה, hahu k'Ben
Hachinai matni lei, his version of that משנה mishnah has it as
דברי בן הכינאי, divrei Ben Hachinai, not as a סתם משנה. stam
mishnah. He has that as in the name of a particular sage,
and therefore his position is that the סתם stam position or the
majority position is that you're allowed to bring it home. Okay, so
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
Rabbi Yochanan, ההוא ירין מביאין בלורי נשים לבי בני. hahu yarin mivi'in
b'lorey nashim l'vei banei. So the bathhouse attendants can bring towels, garments
of women, to the bathhouse. Now we're back to the discussion on
the עמוד א, amud aleph, are you wearing or are you carrying?
So they can wear, so even though maybe it's women's, so maybe
it would seem more like carrying, no, they can have it on
their body as a way of and wear it to the bathhouse,
ובלבד שיתכסה בהם ראשן ורובן, u'velvad sheyitkaseh bahem roshan v'ruban,
but they have to wear it like you'd wear a garment to
use to cover their head and the body, not to wear it
like a type of a scarf.
But you're not allowed to be
going to the bathhouse on שבת? Shabbos? Right, so the funny thing
is all these stories are about the bathhouse, so maybe it's cold
water, maybe it's not the hot water, you know, maybe it's pouring
the hot water on your head rather than immersing in it, like
the גמרא Gemara discussed before. Okay, סכניסא, sakhnisa, צריך לקשור בית ראשה
למטה. tzarich lekasher beis rosheha l'mata.
Now because we didn't get a chance to finish our discussion from
the עמוד א amud aleph apparently, so if you have this סכניסא,
sakhnisa, which apparently is also like a type of a scarf, צריך
לקשור בית ראשה למטה, tzarich lekasher beis rosheha l'mata,
you have to tie the two ends on the bottom or else
it is like, or you know, if imagine a scarf, if you
didn't knot it in front, it would slip off. And therefore, if
there's a concern it will slip off, either that's seen as not
the normal way of wearing it, nobody wears it that way because
it falls off, or no, we're just afraid it will fall off
and you'll pick it up and you'll come to carry. Okay, so
it's going back to how you wear your garments on שבת. Shabbos.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba Rabbi Yochanan, למטה מכתפיים. l'mata mikispayim.
So did I skip a line?
Yeah, what we mean below, we mean it has to be knotted
below the shoulder, the shoulder blades. אמר ליה רבא לבני מחוזא, amar
lei Rava livnei Mechuza, רבא Rava said to the inhabitants of מחוזא,
Mechuza, which was רבא'ס Rava's city, כי מבריתו מאני לבני חילא, ki
mavrisu mani livnei cheila,
when you have to bring garments to the troops, they would have
to sometimes serve the troops on שבת, Shabbos, when you have to
bring garments to them, שרביבו בהו למטה מכתפיים, sharvivu behu l'mata mikispayim,
have it sort of draped down below your shoulders so you can
at least wear the garments and be minimizing your חילול שבת, chillul
Shabbos, because if it's not draped down below the shoulders, it's considered
like you're carrying it. Okay, so that has to do with the
issue we went back to carrying, but primarily the issue about the
concern that you'll come to squeeze out the towel. Now סכין וממשמשין,
sakhnin u'memashmeshin, you can put on the oil and sort of rub
it on your body. תנו רבנן, tano rabanan, סכין וממשמשין בבני מעיים,
sakhnin u'memashmeshin b'vnei mei'in, on שבת Shabbos you can do it on
your stomach, ובלבד שלא יעשה כדרך שהוא עושה בחול, u'velvad shelo ya'aseh
k'derech she'oseh b'chol, but not like you do on the weekday. So
it shouldn't be עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. היכי עביד? heichi avid? So
how should he do? רבי חמא בר חנינא אמר סך ואחר כך
ממשמש. Rabbi Chama bar Chanina amar sakh v'achach kach memashmesh.
First you put on the oil and then you rub because in
the weekday they would rub and put on the oil. I gotta
tell you, I don't understand how it helps to rub and then
put on the oil, unless the rubbing is maybe to like maybe
open up the pores, you know, not to just apply it. I
don't know. But anyway, you reverse the order. רבי יוחנן אמר סך
וממשמש בבת אחת, Rabbi Yochanan amar sakh u'memashmesh b'vas achas, you do
it at the same time rather than first do one and then
do the other. Now it's not clear what's the עובדא דחול. uvda
d'chol. Like, you know, what types of things are considered weekday activities?
Sometimes it's things that are associated with מלאכות, melachos, sometimes it's things
that are associated with like professions, you know, not necessarily מלאכה, melacha,
but the type of work that you do during the weekday. It's
not exactly clear here how the bathing issue and how the oil
issue is anything like that, unless the point is that maybe it
was like a very just laborious process, you know, but it's not
even clear what the עובדא דחול uvda d'chol is. Maybe specifically around
the issue of the בני מעיים bnei mei'in on the stomach because
that would maybe be more רפואה refuah related. But then it's funny
that it says עושה בחול oseh b'chol if that's if the issue
is the רפואה refuah type of concern. So this is like a
very, you know, unclear category of עובדא דחול uvda d'chol and what
types of things fall into it or not. Okay, אבל לא מתעלמין,
aval lo misalmin, you cannot vigorously rub or massage it. אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Rabbi
Yochanan, אסור לעמוד בקרקעיתה של דיומסת מפני שמעמלת. assur la'amod bekarkeita shel
dyumset mipnei sheme'amelet.
You cannot stand on the floor of דיומסת, Dyumset, which is a
type of a river, you know, which would be very like hot
because it causes you to...
and רש"י Rashi says very salty water. and causes you to sweat.
ומרפא U'merapeh and it heals you. So sweating per se is not
the issue, the issue is doing this type of stuff that causes
the sweat as a part of a process of healing. So therefore
it goes back to the רפואה refuah issue. Doing these types of
things like if you take a שוויץ shvitz or whatever, that's actually
a way of a healing process.
But if you're not actually sick and it makes you feel better,
you know what I mean? Like, are they still worried about סממני
רפואה?
sammanei refuah? Yeah, that's a good question.
If it's something that
is can be done in a non-רפואה refuah context, then even if
you're sick it's allowed, right? But if it's something that clearly is
a מעשה רפואה, maaseh refuah, you're right, I mean something that could
go either way, context could very well make the difference. אמר רבי
יוחנן אסור לעמוד בקרקעיתה של דיומסת מפני שמאמלת. Amar Rabbi Yochanan assur
la'amod bekarkitah shel Dyumeset mipnei she-me-amelet. I just did that. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב כל ימיה של דיומסת עשרים ואחד יום. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav kol yameha shel Dyumeset esrim ve'achad yom.
The days, the time, the period of דיומסת Dyumeset is 21 days.
Meaning, its health benefits are only 21 days out of the year.
ועצרת מן המנין, Ve'Atzeret min haminyan, including שבועות. Shavuos. So the גמרא
Gemara says איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they ask the question: עצרת להאי
גיסא או להאי גיסא? Atzeret lehai gisa o lehai gisa? Does it
start at שבועות Shavuos or does it end? If
you say including, then obviously it's an end point, but do the
21 days end with שבועות Shavuos or start with שבועות? Shavuos? So
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דאמר שמואל כולהו שקיטניא מדבחא
ועד עצרת מעלו. de'amar Shmuel kulhu shaktianei midevcha ve'ad Atzeret ma'lu. All
of drinks from the קרבן זבח, korban zevach, זבח zevach is a
זבח, zevach, זבח פסח, Zevach Pesach, from the קרבן korban period, from
פסח Pesach until שבועות, Shavuos, מעלו, ma'lu, are healthy. So therefore you
see that שבועות Shavuos is the end of the period of when
these things are salubrious, if I were to use that word correctly.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says what? 49 days? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says דילמא התם הוא דקמי דקריר עלמא מעלי. dilma
hatam hu dekamei dekarir alma ma'lei. Maybe that's by drinks. By drinks
as the world is colder, when it's colder maybe it's better, and
after שבועות Shavuos it starts getting to be the summertime, those drinks
are not as
effective, medicinal drinks. אבל הכא משום הבלא הוא, Aval hacha mishum hevla
hu, but here it's because of the steam, and therefore כיון דחמים
עלמא טפי מעלי. keivan dechamim alma tfei ma'lei. If the world is
hotter, it's more in the summertime, maybe it's better. So we don't
know if שבועות Shavuos is the beginning or the end of this
period where this is helpful. אמר רבי חלבו, Amar Rabbi Helbo, רבי
חלבו, Rabbi Helbo, now we have a little אגדתא aggadata digression. רבי
חלבו Rabbi Helbo said חמרא דפרוגייתא, hamra de'Prugeita, the wine of פרוגייתא,
Prugeita, which was some very a particular place and some very high-quality
wine, ומיא דדיומסת, umaya de'Dyumeset, and the waters of דיומסת, Dyumeset, קיפחו
עשרת השבטים מישראל. kipchu aseret hashvatim mi'Yisrael. They sort of cut off
the ten tribes from Israel, meaning that these were such indulgences that
they led them to sin and abandon life of meaning and so
on. So it's all the blame were these two things that they
had in their land which were which led them to be overly
indulgent. רבי אלעזר בן ערך, Rabbi Elazar ben Arach, now רבי אלעזר
בן ערך Rabbi Elazar ben Arach איקלע להתם, ikla lehatam, happened to
go there to
פרוגייתא Prugeita which had this amazing wine. ואימשיך בתרייהו, v'imshich batreihu, he
sort of was drawn after it, he became a little addicted to
this wine,
איעקר תלמודו, i'akar talmudo, and actually he forgot all of his learning.
He really became he developed a
dependency and it led to the fact that he forgot all of
his earlier learning. כי הדר אתא, Ki hadar ata, when he came
back and he finally left the place, קם למיקרי בספרא, kam lemikrei
besifra, he got up to read from the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah.
בעי למיקרי החודש הזה לכם, ba'ei lemikrei Hachodesh hazeh lachem, he should
have read the פסוק pasuk החודש הזה לכם, Hachodesh hazeh lachem, this
month is to you.
אמר החרש היה לבם. amar Hacheresh haya libam. So these words all
look very similar, so maybe his eyesight also got affected or his
processing, but instead of reading החודש הזה לכם Hachodesh hazeh lachem he
says this חרש, cheresh, this like
deaf-mute, deaf-mute became their hearts. So basically like your heart gets stopped
up and can no longer receive
תורה Torah is what had happened to him. And even like this
פסוק pasuk which is like the very first מצוה mitzvah that was
given to כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, so it was really like the
סימן siman about how much he had lost. בעו רבנן רחמי עליה,
ba'u rabanan rachamei alei, so the rabbis prayed for him,
והדר תלמודו, vehadar talmudo, and miraculously his learning was restored. So at
least it has a happy ending, but it really speaks about this
danger. What? Okay, one minute, I'll get to the דקדוקי סופרים Dikdukei
Sofrim nice פשט. peshat. והיינו דתנן, V'hainu de'tenan, and that's what we
talk in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי נהוראי אומר, Rabbi Nehorai omer, רבי
נהוראי Rabbi Nehorai says, this is in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, הוי
גולה למקום תורה, hevei gole le'makom Torah, you should exile yourself to
a place of תורה. Torah. Don't stay where it's nice and comfortable
and you should be prepared to give up all of your creature
comforts and go to a place where actually is a place of
תורה. Torah. Number one. So number one, maybe it's referring to just
the dangers of creature comforts, but more significantly, it's about prioritizing being
around other people that are learning. And that's the next part: ואל
תאמר שהיא תבא אחריך, v'al tomar she'hi tavo acharecha, don't think "yeah,
I'll go where I want to, and תורה Torah will follow me,
my students will come to me." Why? שחבריך יקיימוה בידך, she'chaveirecha yekaymuha
beyadecha, you need your colleagues, don't think you're self-sufficient, you need your
colleagues to stay sharp, so stay in a place where there is
תורה. Torah. even if it means giving up some of your comfortable
surroundings
or some say שחבריך יקיימוה בידך shechavereicha yekaiymuha beyadecha right
no yeah I'm reading it the way רש"י Rashi says it ואל
בינתך אל תשען ve'al binatcha al tish'en do not rely on your
own on your own intellect you need your friends you need your
colleagues you need to be in a place of תורה. Torah. תנו
רבנן tanu rabanan the ברייתא braita לא נהוראי שמו lo nehorai shemo
his name wasn't רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai אלא רבי נחמיה שמו ela
Rabi Nechemia shemo his real name was רבי נחמיה Rabi Nechemia ואמרי
לה ve'amrei lah רבי אלעזר בן ערך שמו. Rabi Elazar ben Arach
shemo. It was the רבי אלעזר בן ערך Rabi Elazar ben Arach
that had lost all his תורה Torah because he left and he
went to this place with all the good wine and by the
way now it's seeming to say the message that the reason he
lost his תורה Torah was not just because like you know but
like a type of of a physical dependency on the wine but
also because he wasn't around other sages and that was part of
it maybe that also allowed him to go off the דרך. derech.
Anyway but also he didn't have the environment to help him keep
his תורה Torah sharp and ולמה נקרא שמו רב נהוראי velama nikra
shemo Rav Nehorai שמאיר עיני חכמים בהלכה sheme'ir einei chachamim bahalacha that
he would enlighten the eyes of the sages with הלכה halacha and
look at what happened to him he used to be the great
light and the great teacher and look what happened to him when
he went to a place where there was the wine was too
good and there weren't תורה Torah sages. What did you want to
say Michael?
Just quickly is because the irony was that he's the one that
when was asked what was the you know the greatest thing you
know the five rabbis he said לב טוב lev tov was
so now the irony was he didn't have a heart that was
the depth you know if you will or
ליבא liba it's his heart
went off the תורה Torah after היין והחמרא hayayin vehachamra and then
he was that's what he did.
Okay that's very nice
that's why it says
חשי עלי ליבא chashi alei liba got it got it. אבל לא
מתגרדים aval lo mitgardim that's to read a little bit more you
cannot scrape off the oil. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan אין גורדין במגררת
בשבת ein gordin bemigreret beShabbat you cannot use a specialized scraper on
שבת. Shabbat. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
אם היו רגליו מלוכלכות בטיט ובצואה im hayu raglav meluchlachot betit uvetzoah
so you were asking Michael the clothes issue but anyway here it
says if your legs were dirty with crusted on excrement or plaster
גורד כדרכו gored kedarko then you can scrape it off ואינו חושש
ve'eino choshesh you don't have to worry. But to scrape directly on
your skin that would be considered like maybe a type of a
רפואה refuah or an עובדין דחול uvdin dechol scraping things off isn't
a problem. ושמואל בר יהודה עבידא ליה אימיה מגרדתא דכספא. veShmuel bar
Yehuda avida leh imei magradta dechaspa. שמואל בר יהודה's Shmuel bar Yehuda's
mother made him a silver scraper so רש"י Rashi says it means
לשבת leShabbat so it's a special שבת Shabbos scraper so maybe that's
you know maybe if there was the primary concern was עובדין דחול
uvdin dechol then maybe if it was a special thing maybe somehow
less עובדין דחול. uvdin dechol.
It's still עובדין דחול uvdin dechol it just looks nicer.
I understand well
I use a different toothbrush on שבת.
Shabbat. Okay אין יורדין לקרדומיסא ein yordin leKardumisa you don't go into
this river מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why משום פיקא mishum pika because
of פיקא pika no I'm
kidding פיקא pika means mud and you'll slip and then your garments
will get all wet ואין עושים אפיקטזין בשבת ve'ein osim apiktzin beShabbat
you cannot use a purgative. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabi Yochanan לא שנו אלא
בסם lo shanu ela besam that's only if it's a type of
a thing you drink that makes you throw up אבל ביד aval
beyad to stick your finger in your throat to cause you to
throw up מותר mutar that's permissible which is interesting why isn't that
also דרך רפואה? derech refuah? But you know ask if you're living
in the Roman times then it's not דרך רפואה derech refuah it's
how you eat a good meal when you throw up and then
you eat some more so that seems to be indicated by the
next line. תני רב נחמיה אומר tani Rav Nechemia omer אף בחול
אסור מפני הפסד אוכלין af bechol assur mipnei hefsed ochlin you can't
do it in the weekday because you're wasting food you know throwing
up so you can eat more so it seems like it's not
a רפואה refuah because a רפואה refuah wouldn't be concerned about wasting
food we'd be concerned about you getting better but it seems like
you're just doing it as a way of eating more it's funny
that it doesn't speak about you know the whole sense of you
know the gluttony involved in it itself being problematic anyway but apparently
if you use a liquid that's more of a רפואה refuah and
the last thing for today ואין מעצבין את הקטן ve'ein me'atzvin et
hakatan you cannot somehow do something to arrange the limbs of a
minor. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabi Yochanan ללפופי ינוקא בשבתא שפיר דמי lelapufi yanuka
beShabbata shapir dami however this לפוף lipuf which is some other type
of an arranging of the limbs which is less like you know
somehow drastic or radical or maybe on the opposite it's maybe it's
more necessary that's permissible והנן תנן אין מעצבין vehanan tnan ein me'atzvin
didn't we say אין מעצבין ein me'atzvin what's the difference? שצדי בחומרי
שדרא דמיחזי כבונה shatzedi bechumrei shidra demichzi kevoneh our משנה mishna is
only allowed not allowing you to like really align the spine because
that's like you're building you're like structuring the spine but other types
of arranging of the limbs or bundling of the limbs would be
okay again it's very hard to understand all of this because okay
we get why they're somewhat problematic but I mean my god what's
going to happen if you don't treat this person
and למעשה lema'aseh we're very lenient in all types of cases in
terms of חולה שאין בו סכנה choleh she'ein bo sakana certainly not
to be concerned about the איסור רפואה issur refuah and even we
מתיר matir even דרבננס de-rabanans for חולה שאין בו סכנה choleh she'ein
bo sakana based on the circumstances so we will continue tomorrow.